if you don't have a goal you suffer and
then you get cruel and bitter and
resentful and then you start to actively
try to make the world a worse place and
so so because you can't suffer
pointlessly without becoming bitter and
you can't become bitter without becoming
cruel so you need a name the question is
then the question bitter what you should
name yeah a dream that's for sure so
then the question is what should your
aim be welcome everyone back to the
school of greenness podcast we've got
the legendary Jordan Peterson in the
house good to see you sir
good to see you very excited about this
you've got a book out called twelve
rules for life make sure you guys check
this out you've probably already got it
but if you don't I'm telling you to go
pick it up right now an antidote to
chaos you've had so much attention over
this last couple of years and I've been
digging into the research and just been
fascinated by everything you've been up
to and I just love your stance on the
vision you have for humanity in terms of
how we can all live better lives and I
think you simplify a lot of things in
this book which some things people don't
like to simplify
they like to complicate and I think
that's what's gotten you a lot of
attention is that you try to really
simplify a lot of these well I try to
make everything concrete so that it's
actually implementable right I mean
there's a lot of high-level abstractions
in the book because it ranges up into
the theological and the philosophical
but it's always grounded in what you can
actually do in your life practically you
want to bridge that gap from the highest
abstraction down to the lowest level of
behavior so that it becomes
implementable that's how philosophical
concepts take on their meaning right
because they have to they have to have
some impact on the way you see the world
and the way you act in the world or
they're not fully realized they're not
understood because partly what we mean I
would say when we say that we understand
something it's kind of a state strange
phrase to understand something but it
means to be able to embody it in a shift
of view and a shift of action
and then you've got it it's graspable
it's in your hand embody something in a
shift of view mother they say well
there's the same thing because your
perceptions are very tightly linked to
your actions because of course when
you're acting you're aiming at something
you have to be devoted towards some some
some aim some target would we play that
out in sports all the time yeah that's
why sports are so entertaining for
people is because they dramatize the
idea of aim right and then and not only
of aim but of the pursuit of excellence
in pursuit of that aim that's the game
and the reason it's a spectacle and the
reason that people participate in it is
because it dramatizes something
absolutely essential about life and so
you want to take philosophical
abstraction and you want to use them to
to structure your aim and then your
perceptions organize around that aim and
then you act it out and then you've got
it that's then it's it's become part of
your life it's not just in it's just
it's not just a philosophical
abstraction that floats free in space
why is there so much conflict in in the
world is it because there's so many
different perceptions that people have
well they think should be right or well
sure well part of it is part of it of
course there's conflict because we have
real problems and so life is actually
difficult independent of the of
psychological foolishness let's say
independent of the obstacles that we put
in our own path like this knowledge it's
already it's already fatally challenging
right life is the ultimate challenge
we will die yes yes there is well a
challenge yes well do fear pain although
yes all the things all everything that
goes along with suffering is a challenge
and it's it's it's the full challenge
because it takes everything you have and
so part of the reason we disagree is
because there are complex problems to
solve and then we also disagree because
we're willfully blind and because we're
more ignorant than we should be and
we're not everything we should be and we
tilt towards malevolence from time to
time and we betray each other and
ourselves and so we take a bad law to in
many ways and make it worse no not
always obviously and we don't have to
but that's sort of the baseline that
we're working against I think people are
most disappointed in life when they're
disappointed in themselves you know they
see that they've made things worse than
they had to be
even though the baseline can be pretty
brutal so yeah so the book and all my
lectures I suppose are put forward in an
attempt to take the high level
philosophical abstractions and to make
them into something that's actionable
and to take the next best action in your
life improve your life hmm
so we don't have to suffer as much
mm-hmm well and hopefully also so that
people around you don't have to either
so one of the things I've been talking
to my audiences about is the
relationship between responsibility and
meaning which is and what would you say
it's a it's a constant refrain in the
book it's one of its underlying messages
let's say or themes is a better way of
thinking about it you know if you start
with the presumption that there's a
baseline of suffering in life and that
that can be exaggerated by as a
consequence of human failing as a
consequence of malevolence and betrayal
and self betrayal and deceit and all
those things that we do to each other
and ourselves that we know that aren't
good that amplifies the suffering that's
sort of the baseline against which you
have to work and and and it's
contemplation of that often that makes
people hopeless and depressed and
anxious and overwhelmed and all of that
it and and they have the reasons but you
need something to put up against that
and what you put up against that is
meaning meaning is actually the instinct
that helps you guide yourself through
that catastrophe and most of that
meaning is to be found in the adoption
of responsibility so if you think for
example if you think about the people
that you admire well you think about
when you have a clear conscience first
because that's a good thing to aim at
which is something different than
happiness right a clear conscience is
different than happiness yeah that's
better
yeah that's better guilting yourself
you're not feeling bad about your sister
right you feel that you've just
acclaimed you've justified your
existence right and so you're not waking
up at 3 in the morning in a cold sweat
thinking about all the terrible things
that you've involved yourself in what
you said to someone they shouldn't have
said I you acted or what opportunity you
lost or or yeah or or the things that
you've that you've let go that you
should have capitalized on all of
that and so if you think about the times
when you're at peace with yourself with
regards to how you're conducting
yourself in the world it's almost always
conditions under which you've adopted
responsibility right at least the most
the most guilt I think that you can
experience perhaps is the sure knowledge
that you're not even taking care of
yourself so that you're leaving that
responsibility to other people because
that's pretty pathetic and I unless
you're psychopathic and you know and
you're living a parasitical life and
that that characterizes a very small
minority of people and an even smaller
minority think that's justifiable but
most of the time you're in guilt and
shame because you're not you're you're
not not only are you not taking care of
yourself let's say so someone else has
to but you're not living up to your full
potential and so there's an existential
weight that goes along with that Souls
you suffer even more hmm when you don't
take care of yourself or take the best
actions or do the work that you know you
can do you rely on someone else to
support you financially emotionally and
physically whatever it mean a home
whatever it may be
yeah well because you're not only you're
not only not being what you could be
you're interfering with someone else
being what they could be right so you're
you're you're not only a void you're a
drain Jesus that's a catastrophe and but
we usually don't even know I wearing
that when we're in that situation
because we're in a depressed state or
we're or we don't want to see it you
know you wake up at 3 in the morning and
you know and so and then you think of
the people that you so you admire
yourself or perhaps you can at least
live with yourself when you're taking
responsibility at least for yourself and
so that settles your conscience but then
if you look at the people that you
spontaneously admire and so the act of
spontaneously admiring someone is the
manifestation of the instinct for
meaning right and this is partly why
people are so enamored of sports figures
because the sports figures are playing
out the drama of attaining the goal of
attaining a certain kind of let's say
psychological and physical perfection in
pursuit of the goal that's the drama and
to spontaneously admire that is to have
that instinct for meaning latch onto
something that can be used as a model
and then that model should be
transcribed into
something that's applicable in life you
know when you really like to see in an
athletic performance you really like to
see someone who's extremely disciplined
and in shape
do something physically remarkable but
and and to stretch themselves even
beyond their previous exploits because
you really like to see a brilliant move
in an athletic match but you also like
to see that person ensconced in a
broader moral framework so that not only
are they trying to win and disciplining
themselves in pursuit of that victory
and then stretching themselves so
they're continually getting better but
they're doing it in a way that helps
develop their whole team and that's good
for the sport in general and that
reflects well on the broader culture a
great leader and their team they're
positive they're good sportsmen who
against the competitors yeah I'm
negative towards the other people
they're lifting them up too yeah like
the ultimate that's right so human
that's right so that they can they can
work for their own improvement in a way
that simultaneously works for the
improvement of their team and that and
and for the sport and while I meant to
the degree that that spills over into
the broader culture so much the better
so that's all being dramatized in a in
an athletic event and it's really it's
not philosophical it's concrete right
it's dramatized in the world and that's
what the games represent and so well and
it's partly because well in some sense
life is a game it is in that you're
always the analogy is that in in life
like in sports you're you're you're
setting forth a name and then arranging
your perceptions and your actions in
pursuit of that it and that you also we
generally do it well cooperating and
competing with other people that's also
the game-like element as well all of
that's dramatized in athletics yeah
that's like philosophy for people who
aren't philosophical and I'm not being
smart about that yeah it's like it
really is philosophy for people who
aren't being philosophical because it's
played out you know and you can see it
too you can see the spontaneous
appreciation for the human spirit
manifest itself when you see people rise
to their feet spontaneously in a sports
arena when they see someone do something
particularly remarkable see an athlete
who's extremely trained stretched
themselves beyond what you'd think is a
normative human limit and everyone
celebrates that
spontaneously so it's quite something to
ya to behold and so took me back to a
responsibility and meaning when we're
watching sports or someone and do this
act what does this do for us with in
terms of responsibility and meaning well
it it helps us figure out what we can
imitate give us a model yes it's a model
there's a model of something that I
respect
well even what philosophy is or even
theology for that matter is an abstract
model like it's laid out in words now
the problem often is is it becomes so
abstract that people don't know how to
bring it back down to the total
embodiment yes whereas something like
like the drama of a sports event is sort
of midway between philosophy and action
right and so it's it's not entirely
abstracted because it's not only coded
in words it's acted out visually you can
see an example of what just happens and
you can try to reverse-engineer how they
yes exactly well Italy at least you the
fact that you admire the person means
that you might start to try to act like
them now it's not easy and maybe that
would mean maybe that would mean that
you start to discipline yourself with
regards to a particular sport but it
might also be that you start to mimic or
at least affected in some way by their
their sportsmen sportsmen like behavior
right which is the ground of a certain
kind of ethic because if you can play
well with others
which is sort of the hallmark of a good
sport then that actually means that
you're a reasonably sophisticated and
civilized person it's really important
to learn to play well with others
there isn't that's the ground of ethics
and you can do it there and that's
setting that hopefully you could
translate it into like well well right
that's exactly right that's what goal
well that's what you hope for yeah
that's the goal of this so if the if the
goal of the game is to put the ball
through the ball into the net then the
goal of having games is to produce
people who can take proper aim no matter
where they are right that's exactly what
we're trying to do with with with with
athletics so on so I've been talking to
my audiences a lot about that about and
well and there's more to it too because
if the background of life is is there's
a there's an inner Attica Bellona of
suffering and that's complicated by
let's say malevolence and the proclivity
of people to betrayed themselves and now
which complicates it makes it worse then
the if you don't have a noble aim and
and and if that isn't in viewing your
life with sustainable meaning then you
fall prey to all the catastrophe the
pain and the anxiety and the anger that
that suffering generates and that makes
you bitter because what I'm here to say
is that and correct me if I'm wrong we
must have an aim in our life no matter
what stage of life we're in and if we
don't have some type of aim even if for
a few months of an aim of going
somewhere direction we're gonna the
suffering is gonna be even more
suffering pointless because we're
already gonna face the greatest
challenges that's right
you start already struggling that's
right there's no way adversity is coming
no matter what x range we have big goals
or small little goal or whatever may be
but it's gonna be less suffering if we
have an aim yeah well in not only that
it's worse than that even because the
suffering is zero meaning
well the suffering is pain and the
suffering is anxiety and uncertainty and
the suffering is hopelessness but the
consequence of all that is that you get
bitter and when you get bitter you get
mean and you get cruel and you start to
hurt yourself and other people so it's
not only that if you don't have a goal
you suffer it's that you if you don't
have a goal you suffer and then you get
cruel and bitter and resentful and then
you start to actively try to make the
world a worse place mm-hm and so so
because you can't suffer pointlessly
without becoming bitter and you can't
become bitter without becoming cruel so
you need a name the question is then the
question of course is what you should
name yeah that's for sure so then the
question is what should your aim be now
we have a program it's one of the things
I wanted to talk to you about that day I
I have this website called self
authoring com and that program helps
people write about their life and so
there's a past authoring program to
establish your aim you have to know
where you are it's like you're trying to
orient yourself on a map you can't
orient yourself on a map unless you know
where you are you also have to know
where you're going right so those are
the two relevant things the past
authoring program helps people write
about their life so it's a guided order
by our
we ask people to break their life up
into six epochs six sections and then to
write about the emotionally important
events in those in those epochs and to
detail out why why the positive things
happen and why more of that could
conceivably happen in the future and to
detail out why the negative things
happen and to try to understand why with
an aim to not replicating them in the
future because the purpose of memory
isn't to remember the past the purpose
of memory is so that you you figure out
what went wrong when something went
wrong so you don't duplicate it in the
future that's the purpose of memory and
the past authoring program can help
people catch up and you know you have to
catch up if you have memories that are
older than about a year and a half that
still cause you emotional pain when you
think about them or if you dwell on them
they come spontaneously back to mind
means you haven't it means that there's
part of your life that you haven't
mapped out properly and it still has
emotional valence that's gripping you
you're still holding on to that story or
it's still holding on to you right you
ever got to go
yeah yeah well you haven't been able to
navigate your way through it you there's
a pitfall there that you fell in and you
don't know how to avoid similar pitfalls
in the future and that's why your brain
won't let it go because it's saying
that's what the anxiety systems do it's
like this happened to you it wasn't good
this happened to you it wasn't good this
happened to you it wasn't good fix fix
fix fix it that will never go away
unless you fix it how do you fix it well
you have to figure out why it happened
right that's the first thing is like how
did you how was it that that situation
arose to pull you down and that's not
simple
that's why well that's why we have the
writing program because it's complicated
to think it through
but you but if you face it and you and
you meditate on it let's say and send
you do this voluntarily there's a pretty
high probability that you'll be able to
decrease the probability that will be
repeated in the future so oh well well
we that the second part of the program
helps people do an analysis of their
virtues and their faults the same sort
of idea what's good about you that you
could capitalize on what's weak about
you that you need to fix so that it
doesn't bring you down right and that's
the present authoring but the future
authoring program is probably most
relevant to you and your listeners
because you're in Ch
in helping people establish aims and so
we already talked about the fact that
you need a name in life or that's where
you derive your meeting and without that
things go to hell and and as literally
as that can be taken and so but it's not
easy to ask people to say well it's easy
to ask them what do you want your life
it's a very hard question to answer
because it's too vague and grand day so
we help in the future authoring program
we help people break that down it's okay
so here's here's the situation so put
yourself in the right frame of mind so
what's the right frame of mind
it's like rule 2 in this book treat
yourself like you're someone responsible
for helping here's someone that you are
responsible for helping so what that
means is you have to start from the
presupposition that despite all your
flaws and insufficiencies that it's
worth having you around and that it
would be ok if things are better for you
so you need to take care of yourself
like you're taking care of someone you
care for so there's a bit of a
detachment in that and then the next
thing is ok so now look three to five
years down the road okay you get to have
what you need and want
assuming you're being reasonable and
that you actually want it which means
you're willing to make the sacrifices
that would that would make it possible
what do you mean by reasonable well that
does that's the next thing well within
your grasp that would be something what
if you don't thing is out of your grasp
but you still push hard enough well then
you need an incremental plant right you
need to break that goal down into steps
of raising goal within a year that's
like yeah I mean we've done the work to
master a skill yet yeah yeah well that's
it and you can have a high end goal and
more power to you if you do need it well
you need a pathway to it you know if you
if it's ten stories up above you you
need a staircase to get there right and
so you have to build the staircase to it
and so in the future authoring program
so you're asked first of all okay here's
you get to have what you want to need
that's the proposition but you have to
aim at it you have to define it name at
it so here so then the first thing is
okay uh if you could put your family
together the way you wanted it to be
what would that look like and so that
might be your siblings and your parents
but that also might be you know your
wife or your husband and your kids
assuming that you're at that point in
your life you can have the family you
wanted what would that look like
right okay career same thing you get to
have the career or the job that that is
within your grasp necessary and and
suitable for you if you were taking care
of yourself how are you gonna educate
yourself because you're not as smart as
you should be there's a lot more things
you need to know so you've got to keep
learning and moving forward so you need
to plan for that how are you gonna take
care of yourself mentally and physically
right so how are you going to avoid that
the catastrophic temptations for example
of drugs and alcohol because that pulls
a lot of people down you need a plan for
that you're gonna be a social drinker
how much are you gonna drink how much is
too much what about your drug use you
gotta regulate that so it isn't a
pitfall how are you going to use your
time meaningful and productively outside
of work you need plan for that so that's
there's one other that yeah I think
there are seven initial questions and I
don't I don't remember the last one
oh intimate relationship of course so
you have do you want do you want a
long-term stable intimate relationship
and if you do then how would you like
that to lay itself out you gotta have a
vision for that because if you don't
have a vision you're not gonna aim at it
and if you don't aim at it then you
won't even see the opportunities when
they arise that's the thing that's so
cool I wrote about this in chapter 10
which is be precise in your speech it's
a chapter about the fact that aims
structure your perceptions so for
example once you aim at something your
brain literally that perceptual
structures in your brain in your visual
cortex reorient themselves to calculate
a pathway to the aim and then what they
show you in the world is obstacles to
that path and and open pathways to the
path that's actually how the world
reveals itself just like just like when
you're driving in a car and you have a
map and you or you aim at a particular
place then all the things that are
related to that place show up in the
world it's exactly the same thing
because you are traveling through time
and space right and you need a map and
so so after you answer these seven
questions and you're encouraged to do it
badly
because you don't have to get a reaction
is to just complete it
right because a bad plan is better than
no plan gives you something to improve
so even if your a-game is vague and even
if it's off target if you start aiming
you see your off target then you can
shift and you can make it more precise
start to recognize what you don't want
in that yes exactly so I thought I
wanted this but I don't so let me read
navigate and figure out what I do
exactly and you might have to try a
bunch of you know well you will have to
you can be that's why you shouldn't get
perfection this thing about it you will
absolutely be wrong but you won't be as
wrong as you would have been if you were
aimless right right so it's a so there's
a bit of no man's land no man's land is
no worse than the old man's room is a
bit worse than a bad path yeah that's
exactly right
like that's that's good that's a good
one and it's right it's right you don't
want to be in no-man's land
why did you use that phrase because
that's right that's exactly right I
think um for me the idea of walking
around aimlessly is like the worst idea
in the world it's like zero purpose zero
mission zero certainty at all it's like
walking around in no-man's land right
aimlessly but it's funny too because in
no-man's land everybody shooting at you
all right cuz that's a military term a
no-man's land is the space in the middle
when everyone's vicious you bet so if
you're aimless you're also the place
where everything is shooting at you yeah
so it's a very good metaphor that came
to mind yeah well that's why I worked on
it that's very very cool so then we say
to people okay look now okay now you've
thought about this for a while it's nice
to do this over a couple of days too
because then you get to sleep on it and
that helps reorient yourself so then
okay now you write for 20 minutes don't
worry about grammar or spelling this
isn't a this isn't a composition
exercise right you get to have what you
want three to five years down the road
what does your life look like
hypothetically write it up
okay so then that's the first part the
second part of the exercise so now
you've got your thing day mat think well
I'm motivated because I got my thing to
aim at it's like you're not as motivated
as you could be because you don't yet
have you think to run away from because
if you really want to be motivated you
want to be going somewhere and you want
to be not going somewhere else which
typically is a pain pain or anxiety yet
some some domain of suffering and guilt
legs don't want to feel this anymore
yes exactly exactly so so the other
thing we ask people is okay now take
stock of your weaknesses and imagine
that you let them multiply you got
hopeless and you auger it in and things
is bad for you as they could be in three
to five years what are some examples of
weaknesses that people might have they
lie they procrastinate yeah they avoid
their grandiose their narcissistic their
undisciplined their nihilistic their
aimless all of those things right victim
mentality they take this they take the
the quick way out they pursue impulsive
pleasures they sacrifice meaning for
expediency they don't take care of their
basic responsibilities they fight
stupidly with their parents they don't
they don't negotiate properly with their
spouse they're bitter at work because
they haven't said what they have to say
they haven't thought through what
they're doing tomorrow they drink too
much they smoke too much they take too
many drugs they don't regulate their
yeah just like everyone knows what it
knows and everyone's got a set of
weaknesses that they know about and so
we say all right what are some of your
weaknesses it like three weaknesses that
you know right now you can still work on
and then three things that you think are
really well a lot of things a lot of
things are things that I've taken care
of in my life like I used to smoke when
I was a kid I smoked a pack a day I used
to drink a lot I didn't work out like
there there there I wasn't nearly as
disciplined as I should have been I
wasn't just careful with what I was
saying like and I suppose loose my most
likely negative outcome probably would
have been I really like to drink like
alcohol was a really good drug for me
Isis on that um well partly it was
mostly because the opportunity came up
for me to investigate drug and alcohol
use but I came from a little town in
northern Alberta it was a heavy drinking
town and and that could have been a real
trap for me right you know and and and
so anyway so we have these people say
okay now you know your weaknesses and
you know what particular hell you would
descend to if you allowed yourself to
descend into it because you've probably
had a taste of it it's like you really
let that go and you're in a terrible
place in three to five years because you
haven't done what you should do what
does that look like it's like write it
down so you know because one of the
things you want to have behind you let's
say I have to do something difficult
like go confront your boss it's like
well maybe hope isn't enough to
encourage you to do that you think well
no if I don't encourage if I don't go
confront my boss carefully
right then I'm gonna hate my job and
then I'm gonna drink more then I'm gonna
end up in that little hell place that I
designed for myself it's like oh I'm not
going there well I don't want to talk to
my boss or I don't want to confront my
wife or my husband whatever it is or my
father or my children for that matter
but if I don't then I'll resent myself
forever then at this time you end up
going down this terrible pathway it's
like because sometimes when you're
moving forward you have to do something
difficult you might think well why
bother and the answer is well so I don't
end up in hell yeah about that oh yeah
oh yeah there's that because it's so
deep if you don't experience the pain
now or the difficulty now you're gonna
have a deeper pain later yeah yeah
that's life much deeper pain yeah yeah
and that's why I think that you
mentioned at one point is like putting
ourselves in structured pain like
structured sense of feeling pain
throughout the day whether it be the
tough conversation I don't want to do
that it's painful but I'm going to
because I know afterwards it's gonna
probably feel better it's bit of a
sacrifice right sacrifice stability in
the present for a gain in the future
that's the big discovery of human beings
and we're gonna face works were you a
big athlete growing up no no I was a lot
of small kids get my grade although I
skied and I went cross-country skiing
and it's individual sports mostly with
my dad you understand that in order to
improve as an athlete or in any sport
you have to put yourself through daily
pain yeah right if you want to achieve
that model of excellence that you watch
someone playing basketball as a child
and you see someone living this model
it's gonna be 15 years of deliberate
pain yeah that's a discipline that's it
yeah well I worked out for a long time
with weights you know what so you know
ya dealt it every day yeah I didn't want
to push through the pain but yeah you
knew that would get you a greater result
yeah well then it's easier not to do it
than to do it but not in the long run
yeah exactly you know I really seen the
benefits for example for weightlifting
because I've watched people because I'm
fifty eight fifty how old am i 56 the
great no I'm soon as I'm getting older
and I really noticed the difference
between people and when they aged
between people who laid down a good
physiological platform when they were
young and those who didn't because by
that if you haven't worked out weights
particularly
say you start to get pretty soft in your
30s and your cardiovascular system
starts to go and really early the other
thing too is the best thing you can do
to maintain cognitive ability isn't to
do exercises like Lumosity it's not
brain exercises that keep you sharp it's
exercise so if you're 50
both cardiovascular have weight lifting
if you're 50 you can restore your
cognitive function to the level of the
30 year old through exercise your mental
function hmm through physical eyes yeah
well your brain is a very demanding
organ and if your cardiovascular system
is compromised then you get stupid and
so yeah it's really cool because as you
move and the bigger you get the more
stupid you become yeah well you
compromise you compromise its function
because the brain is a it's a it's it's
the organ that uses more it's very
metabolically demanding and so if you're
not in good physical shape then one of
the things that suffers most greatly is
your cognitive function and so that's
quite an interesting thing to see how
tight that linkage is so in the next
part of the program we have people now
it's okay now you got your vision yeah
even if it's a bad one it's yeah that's
right what's better than no vision at
all right some know maybe you could
improve well think you're trying to get
through a territory you don't understand
and here's your option no map a map
that's not so good but has some things
about it or a great map well obviously
the great map is the thing you want but
the the map that something is way better
than the map that's nothing Plus as you
explore because of your map you could
start to fill in the details you start
to learn you start to overcome stuff you
learn to master skills no journey right
hmm
yeah well that's the other thing too is
like let's say you you aim at something
and you and you develop some skills
along the way and then you get like a
third of the way there and you think oh
that's not for me it's like well yeah
fair enough but now you've still got the
skills you developed you know exactly
why it's not for you now instead of
vague you don't the kid going after
those exactly exactly well and you have
a rationale and then you can bring that
wisdom back even though it's not perfect
you can bring it back to your next plan
and so and take responsibility yes the
next step yes yes and so as you plan you
get better at planning which is the
crucial thing so so then we say to
people take your positive vision
and make it into eight stainable goals
right so and then rank them in a
hierarchy because you need to know what
like a top goal and and incremental
goals yeah and and that well that's the
other thing is break the goals into
incremental goals so that you have a
reasonable probability of succeeding so
because what you want to do this is also
what you want to do with the kid you
don't tell your kid here is an
impossible thing why don't you go out
and fail you say here's something worth
going after here's a step you could take
that would push you beyond where you are
but that you also have a reasonably high
probability of succeeding at right they
called that within a time frame if then
some time frame that's the other thing
you have to parameterize it with regards
to time frame that's right and that puts
you in the zone of proximal development
and that says that's a concept that was
generated by a guy named Vygotsky he was
a Russian developmental psychologist and
the smart one it's where the idea of the
zone comes from to be in the zone and
when you're in the zone you're expanding
your skills in a manner that's
intrinsically rewarding because you're
succeeding and so you want to set if
you're good to yourself you think okay I
need to set a goal but I need to set a
goal that someone is stupid and useless
as me could probably attain if they put
some effort into it and then you got
then you've got it perfectly because
it's not so high that it's grandiose or
impossible that you fail necessarily and
then justify your bitterness it's like
well I couldn't do it well because that
happens to Pete how much all the time
yeah it's like this all the time you
know it's like it's yes exactly well I
set a goal and I didn't attain it so I'm
not gonna set any more goal right it's
like no you set a goal that was
inappropriate for the time frame that's
right you didn't calibrate it properly
and and you're playing a trick on
yourself because you wanted to fail so
that you could justify not having to try
that's why being a victim mmm yeah which
isn't in helpful you're still gonna be a
victim right there's no way out of that
so you know because life is this life is
a challenge that in some sense can't be
surmounted so there's no way out of your
problem but there are certainly proper
ways of dealing with it and so you lay
out eight those eight steps yeah lay
them out and then the next thing is okay
you need a rationale for them because
you're gonna have doubts and other good
of people are gonna put up obstacles
a rational means I mean yeah yeah
justification yeah it's like okay so
here what sort of justification is a
good justification for your goals it's
easy why would it be good for you okay
why would it be good for your family if
you attain that goal why would it be
good for the broader community because
if it's a good goal it should be good
for you that's fine but if it's a really
good goal it should be good for you in a
way that's good for other people in a
way yes exactly and you went if you're
gonna decide what your goals are why not
set up the ones that benefit the largest
number of people simultaneously yes if
you can do that you should start with
your own concerns cuz you have to take
care of yourselves in these first yes
put your own oxygen mask on then put
your child's oxygen mask on yeah right
and then you can as you as you build up
a the basis of competence locally you
might develop enough skills so that you
can expand that outward and it also
gives your goal a certain amount of
nobility and so if someone challenges
you and says well why are you doing that
that seems stupid you could say I'm
doing that because it helps me take care
of myself but it benefits my family and
here's the reasons why and this is the
repercussions out into the broader
community and like people aren't people
who are putting up objections and doubts
aren't aren't armed to deal with that
kind of response and then when you have
those doubts in your mind that plague
you which they and go back to your
reason go back your reasons you slide
that's right say why am I doing this oh
yeah it's because well I have to take
care of myself because otherwise I'm
pathetic and useless and hitter and
cruel and then and I'm going somewhere
terrible so that's a bad idea and here's
how it would help my family and here's
how it would help the community and
that's good enough set of reasons for it
unless I can think of better ones
without better ones that's good enough
because I think the question comes back
to after you know someone can go down
the rabbit hole and say why why am I
doing this and why is this you know
meaningful for me and I think a lot of
people go back to what why am I here in
the first yes yes why am I here hmm what
is the meaning of my life and is this
real or is this just some dream world
well in that people do go back to that
and then they get stuck on that yeah
what none of this even matters because
why am I even here well the thing is is
that that's a
self-defeating set of propositions in
some sense because the consequence of
being stuck there is no reason you stuck
there to begin which is because you're
not very happy about the fact that life
is intrinsically tied up with suffering
because you wouldn't be asking that
question to begin with okay so if you
let that pull you in and take you down
all it does is make the suffering worse
it's not helpful and then and then the
cascade that we talked about happens you
suffer stupidly and pointless in her you
get bitter give curl yeah you make
everything worse it's like that's your
answer is it you're gonna make
everything worse it's bad enough you're
gonna make it worse mostly people won't
do that consciously yes so you think
well what's the alternative well here's
one if you have a sufficiently noble
purpose the suffering will justify
itself and I think I think that's
empirically testable and I do believe
it's the case because I've watched
people do very difficult things like
people who work in palliative care wards
so all they're ever dealing with is pain
and death right and they can do it I get
up in the morning they go to work and
they take care of those people they lose
people on a weekly basis and yet they
can do it and what that shows is that if
you turn around and you confront the
suffering voluntarily you find out that
you are way tougher than you think it's
not that life is better than you think
life is as harsh as you think it might
even be worse but you are way tougher
than you think if you turn around and
confront it and so then what you
discover is that there's a spirit within
you that pursues something that can
pursue something meaningful that has the
resilience and the strength to contend
properly with the catastrophe of
existence without becoming bitter that's
actually the central so and then I would
say that's one of the central themes of
the 12 rules for life is that make no
mistake about it like the first noble
truth of Buddhism life is suffering this
is true and it's worse than that because
it's suffering contaminated by
malevolence that's the baseline but and
so that's very pessimistic but the
optimistic part is that you are so damn
tough you can actually not only deal
with that you can improve it it's like
oh well that's a horrible situation but
it turns out that I'm armed for the task
well that's that's a great thing for
people to know and I do believe I think
the fact that we're armed for the task
is even more true than the fact that
life is
Rafik contaminated by malevolence we're
stronger than things are terrible so and
things are pretty terrible so that means
we're pretty damn strong Wow
yes it's a very good thing to know and
it's not naive optimism it's a very
different thing it's like no things are
terrible they're brutal and you are so
damn tough you can't believe it so wow
what's what's been the biggest challenge
in your life that you've had to overcome
or the biggest suffering that took me
the longest to get beyond to improve
you
having them bring you down is not
helping the person it has the problem
it's the same with with my daughter it's
like had my wife and I deteriorated as a
consequence of her condition a that
would have been horrible for her because
then she would have had to bear the
weight of watching her illness destroy
her family right which have that guilt
oh Christ
yes I mean that's one of the terrible
things about having a a very bad illness
is that not only does it do you in but
you can see it taking its toll on the
people around you I think that might
even be worse welcome everyone back to
the school of greenness podcast we've
got the legendary Jordan Peterson in the
house good to see you sir good to see
you very excited about this you've got a
book out called twelve rules for life
make sure you guys check this out you've
probably already got it but if you don't
I'm telling you to go pick it up right
now an antidote to chaos what's been the
biggest challenge in your life that
you've had to overcome or the biggest
suffering that took me the longest to
get beyond to improve oh I think that
was probably I wrote about this in the
last chapter in my book which is called
pedicab when you encounter one in the
street and it's about it's about dealing
with you know you think what's the worst
thing that can happen to you well I
think the worst thing is that you do
something really horrible and you screw
up your life and everyone's life around
you that's that just live with it yes
yes so you have to live with knowing you
did it it's like that's rough man
that's it worse than dying yes and then
you don't remember there are worse
things dying yeah but I think the the
hardest existential situation that I've
been in is the situation with my
daughter because she was very very ill
and she had rheumatoid arthritis she had
arthritis it wasn't rheumatoid type and
she had 40 affected joints that has
started to bother her when she was 2 but
really manifested itself fully when she
was 6 and some of the medical treatment
helped but when she was 15 14
14 through 16 first her hip
disintegrated and then her and so she
had that replaced after walking around
on it for like a good year and then her
ankle disintegrated on her other foot
and she had to have it replaced and so
there were two years of absolutely
brutal pain for her like brutal daily
excruciating pain and and we were really
running around trying to figure out what
to do about it because the hip wasn't
too hard to replace you know because
surgeons are actually pretty good at hip
replacements but ankles are still so
many balls touching oh yeah yeah and so
and just watching that and and and while
watching what it was doing to her
because she was in enough pain at one
point just about broker you know and I
mean you know you and I you have a
situation where you were in pain for a
night and couldn't sleep it's like yeah
fine so multiply that by five and
extended over two years Jesus Christ
yeah and she was on like huge doses of
opiates and so that was sedating her and
so that made her look drunk in public
and she can only stay awake for about
six hours a day and she had to take
ritalin to stay awake because otherwise
she was just sleeping all the time and
and it was a very bad autoimmune
condition and so wasn't only manifest in
in the joint deterioration and the pain
because arthritis is also very painful
and forty joints happens to be quite a
loss so one joint was brutal yeah right
no it was absolutely brutal beyond
belief as a father or a parent how do
you navigate that emotionally yourself
yeah well that's what that chapters
about I mean so were there so what do
you do when when things are too much
well one of the answers is you narrow
your timeframe and the other answer is
you look for occasions of grace and
beauty where you can get them so when
she had a dog that really helped yeah
you know so that was something that was
with her all the time and we tried to
put things in her life that that she
could care for she had a whole raft of
pets although she was allergic to almost
everything so most of them were lizards
oh yeah I know what people say guinea
pigs like oh I love this kitty Vegas
okay and then you know three hours later
she'd have a big role
like Harry's dogs right so the dog
luckily the dog she could tolerate and
so we had the dog for her and but what
are one of the things you do when you're
in the situation like that it's just a
bloody ongoing nightmare is that you you
shrink your timeframe it's like well
what are we gonna do in a year it's like
oh god you can't even think about that
it's about six months yeah a week
tomorrow today the next hour yeah so
that's what you're really doing great
you shrink your timeframe till you can
tolerate it so you're not planning out
year yes because then you'll go crazy
yeah it's too much uncertainty yeah you
think okay how can I make the next hour
the least amount of awful possible
that's what you do at someone's deathbed
no you shrink your timeframe and that
and that's what you have to do how does
that play into the self authoring
program if you have this vision for
yourself and you're mapping out a year
to three five years ahead yeah well
sometimes you know we navigate yeah
that's right you have to read navigate
you have to say no better than that
yeah because even the best laid plans of
mice and men go astray you know I mean
that's part of being alive and so you
have your mouth but you know if you get
a flat tire along the way is to have to
stop and fix your car or maybe the
bloody thing bursts into flames you have
to get in there you know so I mean your
your your ascent towards your goals can
be punctuated by unexpected catastrophe
and then well then hopefully you've made
yourself into a resilient person at that
point and the catastrophe is no worse
than it has to be and you're not making
it worse I mean one of the things we
were fortunate about is that by the time
she got really ill my my relationship
with my wife was pretty well put
together and my relationship with my son
my who's younger than her was also well
put together and so he was an absolute
trooper man because most of her a lot of
his teenage life in particular there was
a huge amount of focus on the suffering
of his sister and we were like right up
to here with that it was just it was
enough and he conducted himself
admirably he didn't if he cause trouble
we didn't know about it he kept it to
himself you know and I don't mean he was
hiding I mean he dealt with it and he
spent a lot of time at home and he
didn't do any unnecessary stupid things
and he put up with his sister and his
parents who were on an jallat without
adding a dish
you know catastrophe and misery and
grief to it and when she was a little
bit crazy and was leaning on him too
hard or bothering him he was there to
support her and it was massively helpful
and you know I wasn't any more my wife
and I were any more crazy towards each
other than we had to be and so there
wasn't like any additional stress during
those periods of time cos yeah any extra
would have been like that's right that's
right how are you able to
compartmentalize or just focus on your
your career at that time you know
lecturing or writing or whatever maybe
it well that's also part of the vision
of Hell it's like well what's the
alternative you let things go and you
make them worse it's like not showing up
and yeah just know there's no excuse for
that it's like how did you how did you
say
was it a compartmentalizing of like okay
it's 9 o'clock or 8 o'clock in the
morning I'm going to work yeah and then
yeah well we made rules and we talked
about some of them like some of the
rules were we didn't talk about my
daughter daughter's illness after 8
o'clock at night that was the rule it's
like no sanity
well we it's it's a war you wear
yourself out in a week you're dead and
everyone suffers a lot so you got to
keep going through however long this is
going to be and so what yeah what do you
have to do well you have to sleep you
have to sleep it's time to stop talking
and go to sleep yeah yeah well and I had
learned some of that because I've been a
clinical psychologist for a long time
and so I've been dealing with people's
problems and you learned how to you know
you think well how can you go home when
when you have all of those problems to
contend with it's like well eh they're
not your problems they're not going away
right no and they're not going away and
and having them bring you down is not
helping the person who has the problem
it's the same with with my daughter it's
like had my wife and I deteriorated as a
consequence of her condition a that
would have been horrible for her because
then she would have had to bear the
weight of watching her illness destroy
her family right which have that guilt
oh Christ yes I mean that's one of the
terrible things about having a very bad
illness is that not only does it do you
in but you can see it taking its toll on
the people around you I think that might
even be worse I mean this is gradations
of Hell but still that's so you also
can't
allowed that to happen if you have a
loved person around you and they're ill
you have a moral obligation not to let
it tear you down because then it's on
them that's no good and you think well
how can you remain healthy and strong in
the face of the terrible suffering of
someone who's close to you it's like
well you want well that's it
the alternative is worse you want me to
get saved and get a read and not be able
to take care of you or me right and then
we when we both surround faster right
not helpful
what about did she ever go through a
play server I guess I guess some people
do this where you know kids who have
some type of autoimmune or some type of
disease or whatever maybe they didn't
necessarily you know they were born with
it or aren't happy you know somehow it's
not like they ate something themselves
they weren't necessarily response and
himse right I mean yeah was she
responsible for causing all these you
know all the pain in her body or was it
just something that happened
well that's what we told her is just
well this life kid is a lot it's not you
we also told her very very many many
times and we're very careful about this
do not use your illness as an excuse as
soon as you do that you can't tell the
difference between the illness and your
character that's right so don't let it
turn you into a victim even though it's
good obviously it's a catastrophe like
we were very clear about that and that
wasn't her fault you know but that she
still had to bear up under it as well as
possible and to do everything she could
and not use it as an excuse and we
talked to her about that a lot and we're
clear about it because and I've seen
this is one of the things I really just
like about what the universities are
doing with disability it's like
everybody gets a disability it's like
well no wonder because people have hard
lives you know it's like it's very rare
to find someone who isn't suffering
under an undue load of some sort there's
something wrong with or there's
something wrong in their family that's
serious or they have terrible economic
pressure like there's something wrong
it's like okay we should make allowances
for you it's like oh yeah what
allowances what exactly does that
entitle me to well I tell you man that's
a murky place you do not want to go
because then you don't know anymore it's
like well what's my responsibility I
mean I have this undue burden to bear
well how does that mitigate my
responsibility
well the answer is as little as possible
you don't go there because you get
confused and and as soon as you get
confused well then the illness has not
only got you physiologically it's got
you psychologically and then you're in
deep trouble and so we were also very
very clear and to her great credit as
far as I can tell like I wouldn't say
she never used her illness as an excuse
because never is a lot you know or never
is an extreme but she certainly
withstood the temptation to do it
habitually and to warp her character as
a consequence and she did figure out
what was wrong with her and fixed it and
so now she doesn't have any of these
she's healthy now while she still has
some residual damage from from
everything that happened like I just
found out yesterday she went to Chicago
to have her ankle checked out because it
isn't working very well and they told
her that she had to have the old
replacement taken out and a new one put
in so but but in her realm of
catastrophe that actually constitutes
nor news that's not as bad as it could
be right so strangely enough so it's not
like she's out of the woods but so you
taught her from an early age that I'm
sorry to cut you off no no no Platt even
though she had a you know let's just for
this state of the conversation a
physical disability right she wasn't as
able-bodied physically as the majority
of people who was that clear to say that
you told her like never allow that to
give you special privileges well never
allow that to be never know it wasn't
that exactly it was never used that as
an excuse to not do something you could
do even without stir things yes because
it's the there's a deception element
there it's like well I don't want to do
that and I have this illness and then I
get away that's right I don't use your
illness as a means of getting away with
something yeah because you'll blur the
line then you'll saucily use that the
rest your life right and if you do that
a hundred times
you'll be so confused about what's
illness and what's and what's not that
you'll not know you won't know anymore
and maybe you won't be able to figure it
out again and then you're in a very bad
place you know there was some things
that she had to have done that were
allowances like when she was doing exams
she had to type because she couldn't
write was writing you know and she
couldn't sit
on the floor cross-legged so she had to
sit in a chair like things that she
actually couldn't do but she still did
it work yes she did I can't take the
test yeah I can't do the exam at all
yeah but she was able to do it with
different circuits yes right right right
and so and and the consequence of that
was that once she she figured out that
most of what was causing her what was
bothering her all of it by the looks of
it was a consequence of it a set of
extreme sensitivities to almost every
sort of food so she hardly eats anything
now see only thing she eats is beef
that's it beef salt water that's it
nothing else that's it yeah that's it
and she's been eating that way for well
mostly for about three years but almost
completely for a year and she feels fine
she's a hundred percent she has no
symptoms no vegetables no supplements
that's it beef salt I'm serious she'll
never cheats Wow never because she
doesn't to feel pain and suffering yes
well it takes it if she if she eats the
wrong thing she has a terrible rut
catastrophic emotional and physical
reaction for a month Wow this actually
limited all food and try one thing at a
time yes yes yes and took about three
years to figure out so yes Wow is right
I can't it's absolutely beyond
comprehension it's a diet that I follow
almost almost entirely now just beef
salted water yes I've been eating that
way for about three months and I've been
on an extremely little carb diet for
about two two and a half years something
like that
so because I both my wife and I have
autoimmune symptoms yeah and she got all
of them your daughter yes she got all
smacks behind by a yes that's right so
and so but when she sorted out what was
wrong she convinced me to also try what
she was doing and it's being
extraordinarily helped really need to
yeah
so you know who would who would have
guessed it so anyway so what you do when
when things are too much for you is you
you narrow your timeframe I also an
ruled in Chapter 12 you know what
there's a there's a fair bit of
discussion in there about fragility and
vulnerability which is really what you
confront when you have a sick kid it's
like oh my god how can the world be
constituted so that a child can unfairly
suffer in this manner it's like okay
here's a way of thinking about it all
right take away everything from your
child that makes them fall
let's say I have a three-year-old it's
like well three-year-olds they're kind
of cute they run around their their
little in there and they're vulnerable
obviously but that makes them cute and
attractive and and and and lovable all
of the vulnerability that's built into
that so you think well you move remove
that one by one well they're 8 foot tall
now and they're made out of steel and
their parts are replaceable and they
have artificially intelligent brain like
you replace them obviously this is
hypothetical with a with a superhuman
robot that doesn't die it's like you
fine but where's the three-year-old
right so one of the things I thought
about when I was writing this was you
know when you love someone especially
well when you love someone you love them
not only despite their fragility but
also because of it and so then that's
the price you pay for it it's like well
you wouldn't they wouldn't be who they
were if they weren't they wouldn't be
who they were if they weren't fragile
and limited in their particular way and
the fact you like to have them around
you think oh well that I mean I guess
you think that that fragility and
vulnerability is justifiable it's like
well then you can't allow that it's
resistant to make you bitter because you
can't have it both ways you can't have
them being vulnerable and cute and and
interesting and and small and and and
needing care but striving to to to
develop and grow you can't have that
without them also being prone to pain
and destruction and vulnerability and so
yeah take your choice and then what do
you do teach them to be strong that's
what you do you don't get rid of the
vulnerability you teach them to be
strong yeah so and that's that that's
also a theme that runs through the book
and in many many ways is that's you
don't protect your children in fact you
do you do the opposite you expose them
to the world as much as you possibly can
and you make them strong that's the best
antidote to their vulnerability not to
protect them
there's no protecting people we already
established that life's a fatal game
there's no protecting people but you can
definitely make them strong and maybe
you can make them strong enough to
transcend that that's the goal man so is
there anything that you wish you would
have done differently with your daughter
or
son that you didn't do not have any
Greek not have any great significance I
mean I I have I have wishes I suppose
from time to time that things could have
been different I I spent less time on
the positive aspects of my son and my
daughter because we were contending with
catastrophe so frequently and so you
know my both my kids have a variety of
interesting talents and it would have
been better perhaps to have had the time
to develop those more thoroughly but you
know and my son well he I wouldn't say
he didn't get as much attention as he
needed he didn't get as much attention
as I would have liked to have paid him
mm-hmm but by the same token it isn't
obvious that it's being bad for him
because it required him from a very
early age to grow the hell up and we
relied on him right from the time he was
a young kid to make intelligent
decisions we assumed he would make
intelligent decisions he was consulted
with regards to decisions and so and it
also made him into someone who is who is
very self-sufficient and capable of
taking care of himself so it might have
be nicer for me I suppose to have spent
more time with him but but he lives down
the street from me now and I spend time
with him and we have a great
relationship and so it's just it's you
know and as he has a very good
relationship with his sister and so it
turned out as well as it could have
right so but that didn't mean that those
years in there they were brutal there
was some brutal times madness but one
night in particular like she was in
absolutely absolute agony and I couldn't
get it under control and I could see
well because I am a clinician I could
see I thought god damn it I'm gonna
ender end up taking her to CAMH that's
the psychiatric hospital cuz it looks
like it's gonna break her really god
damn it
I couldn't see a way to to resolve it
but it pushed her right to the brink but
but not over so and there was another
episode after after she
have removed have hip replaced she was
put in a rehab home hospital for a while
and she was the youngest person in it by
like 60 years and they treated her
terribly it was a terrible place mean
mean blind nurses and very very badly
run and they traumatized her the
hospital was a worse experience than the
damn surgery and so that that was that
took her quite a while to recover from
but she did recover from it do you ever
think now you know since your clinical
kind of clinical psychologist and you've
done all this research and work and
studies do you believe that your
daughter was meant to experience this
for you to kind of test your ability to
be with her and do you think she would
have been able to grow in the way she is
now as someone who didn't have the
practice that you had well I think it
was fortunate for all of us that well my
wife too like my wife had worked in
palliative care as a volunteer and she
was a massage therapist for a long time
she's very good at and my wife has it
real she's a really tough person and if
you don't need help and you want it
she'll cut you into ribbons but if you
need help she will really help you yeah
so she's really good at differentiating
between people who actually need help in
which case she is right there
and people who could stand up on their
own and if you can't stand up on your
own and you could if you could stand up
on your own end you aren't you don't
want to be around her because she will
she will put you in your place and it
was so funny because our kids used to
bring their friends over all the time
when they were teenagers which we
actually quite liked and what we had
rule for the teenagers which was we're
really happy you're here but if you do
something stupid and you never get to
come back that's actually okay with us
right so they knew that and it was no
joke because we were happy they were
there and they were welcome but we were
perfectly happy to dispense with them if
they misbehaved forever and so but what
was really funny was that the kids would
come over the teenagers would come over
and they were pretty afraid of me to
begin with
but after being around for a couple of
weeks they were way more afraid of my
wife
yes that was very funny yeah because
she's you know she's some quite a
pleasant person and she's not it she's
only five foot two so she
but although she's you know she's
imposing enough because she's also in
good physical shape but it was because
I'm actually kind of soft-hearted and
she's not soft-hearted although she can
really take care of people who need to
be taken care of
so no so I think you know Mikayla had a
fortunate fortunate circumstance in that
sense because both of us had a lot of
experience dealing with catastrophe and
so when it came along we weren't we were
overwhelmed by it what but it wasn't
because we didn't know what we were
doing we knew what we were doing it was
just even though we didn't know what we
were doing as much as might be possible
that doesn't mean that we could deal
with it because it was well it took us
it took us what must have been seven or
eight months to arrange the ankle
surgery and there was a waiting list in
Canada at that point of I think three
years actually they wanted to fuse her
foot which is a really bad thing for
them for someone young and so we looked
at India we looked in we looked all over
the world for ankle surgery like really
everywhere and finally the government in
Canada was actually quite helpful we
found a private clinic in Vancouver that
did the surgery and the and and the
Ministry of Health and Ontario was quite
helpful to us at that point but we are
scrambling to well what what should we
do should we ever drink'll replacement
what sort of replacement who do we talk
to well what about this waiting list
three years like no man I can't we got
was a week oh yeah that's three years
that was just beyond did you ever doubt
yourself in terms of your ability and
your research and your studies did you
ever say to yourself like man if I can't
you know figure this out then all of my
work is for nothing well no I never
thought it was for nothing but I
certainly I certainly doubted whether or
not we were going to be able to figure
out figure this out Lee yeah one of you
cuz you thought you know you know and at
that time you're extremely educated
research you know you see a lot did you
did that give you a fear of like well if
I can't figure this out then knowing of
course of course well her her prognosis
was multiple early joint replacements
and and that was like that was the good
news because the bad news is well how
many and and how many can you stand and
and when does that kill you like you
know so her real prognosis was plenty of
pain with an early death
you know because well even now even now
you know like the surgeon who talked to
her yesterday said well because he
talked to her about the risk of
amputation in the future it's like well
this is the second joint revision it's
like maybe this would last 15 years we
don't know what the hell is going to
happen now well so our response to that
is that's 15 years from now it's like
who knows the other than well things are
better now for how people understand how
to replace an ankle then they were I
think it was 10 years ago that she had
this one replaced and it helped it
wasn't perfect her hip is perfect the
ankle has always been trouble but way
less trouble than it was and so well you
struggle forward the best you can and so
I suppose she could adapt to an
amputation if that was necessary but at
the moment it isn't necessary but
multiple amputations is not something to
really be looking forward to when you're
16 you know when they were gonna put her
on corticosteroids to control her her
her inflammation and that would have
produced Cushing's disease and so that
makes your face all puffy and it makes
you gain weight and so it's very
physically disfiguring so we decided not
to go down that route and Wow yeah well
but you know it's it's worked out thank
God it's quite the miracle and she had a
baby a year ago and we were never sure
that was going to happen so grass thank
you yes yes that's for sure so now we
have this respite where she's healthy
and the last time I saw her she was
looking great like she's just glowing
she's so healthy I can't believe it it's
just beyond belief Congrats on all the
hard work you've done to make a make it
a possibility yeah well we avoided the
worst excesses of hell during the
catastrophe so that's something and it
did allow her the space to figure out
and my wife and always thought that diet
had a relationship to it and we
investigated that like there's a good
literature that shows if you have
arthritic symptoms and you stop eating
if you fast they go away so that's
interesting it's like well food must be
causing it yeah but once you start to
eat again to survive what you eat it
comes back it turns out no not no matter
what almost no matter what because she's
sensitive to virtually everything but
she isn't sensitive to meat and so it
turns out that if you eat meat you can
live so that's a big difference between
being sensitive to everything and not
being sensitive to one thing yeah and so
so it's it's harsh diet it's made
travelling difficult although I can eat
in restaurants because most restaurants
can cook a steak with nothing on it and
that's made things much easier while I'm
traveling but whatever whatever it's
working so thank God for that amazing
do you believe do you think
hypothetically if your daughter was
healthy and never had any complications
that you would be the man you are
impacting people that the success you
know the attention you beginning do you
think you'd have as much when we've
written the twelfth chapter riots for
sure do you think in general you would
still be able to have the ideals the
belief the fortwo that you have to reach
people and really impact yeah I think so
but I I know what you're know what
you're saying you know your question is
well to what degree is adversity
character building and the answer to
that is plenty but I was already like I
said and it was the same with my wife we
weren't naive people you know I'm not
because I had an extensive clinical
practice I was dealing with with heavy
level adversity always hours a week your
daughter
no no but there were you know there were
other problems in my family and so forth
that I dealt with as well and so we were
already we'd already
I think garnered most of what we could
from confronting adverse situations you
know now did that add a different level
to it
it probably probably fire tested our
relationship our familial it probably
brought our family closer together all
things considered I saw the same thing
happen when my wife's mother died died
she died of pre-frontal dementia and she
developed it quite young about it
started to really manifest itself in her
early 50s and she died when she was 70
and she fell apart over you know 18
years and she was very physically
healthy and her husband who was quite
the man about town when he was a young
guy real extrovert he was a real
character in our home town he took care
of her so well it was absolutely
jaw-dropping man every time she slipped
he'd step up to the plate and he he took
care of her until he couldn't lift her
out of her chair anymore and he was
getting old too and so she wasn't in an
old-age home for very long and then we
were around when she died you know over
the couple of days just before her death
and her family her sister's a palliative
care nurse her other sisters a
pharmacist and Tammy's had the
experiences that already described and
then her father really stepped up to the
plate so the whole family gathered
around for that and they acted
impeccably throughout it I would say
they took care of their mother very
carefully while she was dying and they
pulled together and one of the
consequences of that which was so
interesting is that although their
mother died and that was a terrible loss
there Barnes that connected them all of
them strengthened to the point where I
would say that was almost compensation
for the loss of their mother so that was
really interesting to see what happens
even in a dire circumstance if people do
do what they can't no I'm not saying
that that's gonna work for every
situation because I know people get cut
off at the knees and sometimes you hit a
tragedy that well that's fatal you know
that you cannot rectify it's a real
catastrophe but it was very interesting
watching that because they were alert
and awake around the deathbed and they
weren't fighting with each other at all
there was no familial squabbling because
you can imagine that that would happen
because everyone's stressed and then you
can just imagine how terrible that would
make something that's already awful
there was none of that they focused
their attention on her you know they
gave her water when she needed it and
they watched her and they made
they made this terrible thing the least
amount of awful it could be and it
definitely pulled them together like
they're that whole family including me
is closer because of what they went
through and also how they went through
it and it's probably the case well I
would say it definitely advanced the
maturity of my son because he was called
and I told him look kid like you can't
add anything to this we're up to here
you have to conduct yourself properly
because otherwise everything's going to
shake and fall we can't have more of
this you can't bring any and anything
unnecessary into this and it was an
all-star it was it was remarkable
Shannon and he who is only in grade 10
when most most of this happened and your
friends are pretty damn important when
you're in grade 10 and he's stuck around
a lot to be helpful so yeah it was
really good for him man yeah well he
yeah he's a good character he's he's
he's quite quite something and it was
very helpful he was very helpful to his
sister they had their fights obviously
Lawrence she was often unreasonable and
nobody you know rod when you're strung
out and you get a view of anything but
pain yeah god she went through so much
like even watching her withdraw from the
opiates because she was on them for a
year and a half but she just quit well
as soon as she was done her sir just
like I'm not taking these anymore and
she had formication which is the
sensation of ants crawling on you like a
month god she just just sailed through
it's like I'm done with these yeah yeah
you guys have been through a lot
yeah a lot yes your what's your biggest
fear now moving forward in your in your
own life Oh making a mistake at the
moment because I got beam I've been the
subject of so much public attention in
the last two years and like I've been in
this situation where well even things I
didn't say have also almost been fatal
because people take them out of context
right you know but I'm my biggest fear
has been that I do something careless
and
and that there are like serious
cascading consequences to you like
you've done something careless or well
everyone's done something careless right
you know but I've been pretty careful I
mean I was fortunate so when this
political scandal blew up around me and
in Canada when I opposed some
legislation that I thought was
reprehensibly constructed you know the
the the radicals on the left in
particular came after me hard and but I
was fortunate because you know they
called me every name under the book and
went after my character and you know I
suppose there was some degree of that
was understandable to some degree
because if you stand up against
something if you stand up against the
radical right well maybe your communist
might no probably not because you don't
have to be a communist to not like the
radical right but if you stand up
against the radical left or maybe you're
a Nazi well probably not but you might
be and so it's certainly in the interest
of the people who are proponents of the
philosophy of the radical left to assume
that you're a Nazi because then they
don't have to deal with you and so
that's what happens you throw yourself
into the fray people try to localize you
and they do that by saying well maybe
you're this may be this may be this may
be or this it's like well yeah maybe not
to and but I already had 250 hours of
lectures up on YouTube at that point so
people could actually go and see what I
had said because virtually every word
I'd ever said to students in a
professional capacity not not every word
because I didn't tape every lecture sure
but I taped multiple years of lectures
and so people went over those with a
fine-tooth comb trying to find out if
there's anything I'd ever said that was
and they couldn't find anything and that
was because I'd be very careful with
what I say ever since I was about 25 I
started paying attention to what I was
saying and not and trying very hard not
to say things that I would trying not
try very hard not to say things that
something in me objected to so and well
that seems to have been provided me with
a buffer and so people came to my
website because they were interested in
well before the political
stuff blew up I had a million views on
YouTube which isn't nothing
a million of anything is a lot but then
when the political scandal started to
break
yeah then people came for them but
stayed for the content and so and that's
really useful
yeah well it's well and it's not that
surprising well you know because of what
you do it's like people there's a great
hunger for information that is practical
and useful and that helps people find
meaning in their lives and orient
themselves there's a great hunger for
that and most of my lectures were
derived from solid psychology some of it
experimental some of the biological some
of it from from from the domains of
neuroscience a lot of it from great
clinicians it's not surprising that
people find it helpful because well
great clinicians were great because they
were really helpful and so to distill
that and to offer it to people in a
digestible form to have that have a good
effect on them well that's that's what
you'd expect that's what the whole
discipline is about and so that's been
that's been great these these public
lectures that I've been doing so I think
I've done 50 of them in about 45
different cities now in about three
months and the average theater size is
between 2,500 and 3,000 people and
they're unbelievably positive events
because people come there and we talk
mostly about the political spectrum and
why there's room for voices on the left
and why there's room for voices on the
right and where the parameters of that
should be because both of those can
descend into extremism and that's not
good and the role of individual
responsibility and individual
sovereignty and the necessity for people
to develop a vision the sorts of things
that we already talked about and
virtually every one that's coming there
they're not coming for political reasons
even though that's the story you hear
from the more ideologically possessed
journalist types because they see the
world that way they can't imagine
anything else could possibly be
happening but the people who are coming
to these lectures are coming because
they are doing everything they possibly
can to make their lives better so and so
and it's lovely to talk to people like
that because mazing it is it's great
it's literally great school greatness
baby right exactly
I've got six minutes to be mindful of
your time in your schedule and I won't
ask you three Falana o'clock okay so if
that's okay yeah you bet so as much as I
would love for you to go on for another
few hours on these answers so I can get
to the last question I'll do my dance my
brief I wish I could go on longer so
what to have you come back next time
here in LA
the first one is what is your purpose
now moving forward and through
everything you've had in your life
what's your purpose moving forward well
I have I'm specific I'm I'm what's my
purpose what am i aiming at well I'm
going to I did a series of biblical
lectures last year I did 15 lectures on
Genesis I'm going to continue doing that
so in November I'm going to start with
the Exodus stories and what I'd like to
do over the next 15 years is make my way
through the whole corpus of biblical
writings so that's one major goal I want
to write another book I've written half
of it already which will be a follow up
to twelve rules for life because I
actually had laid out on a site called
Korah forty rules and so I'll do that
and and write in another couple of books
I suspect over the next few years I the
touring I'm going to continue I have ten
cities coming up in Canada and another
twenty in the US and then twelve in
Europe and I'm going to go to Australia
in February and then back to Europe I
think in April so there's lots of
touring on the horizon and it's it's for
the reasons I already described I'm
having I don't the lectures differ every
night although there are themes that
constantly emerge and I'm using those as
an opportunity to have a detailed and
engaged discussion with the audience
about how we might proceed forward
individually and collectively so that we
can make things consciously better and
why that's associated with necessary
meaning and why that's a moral
obligation so it's a dialogue about
responsibilities and not rights even
though right rights are only important
insofar as they set up the space for you
to shoulder your proper responsibility
and as a sovereign citizen you have the
responsibility for the integrity of the
state resting on your shoulders and it's
something that if you don't take
seriously then the state shakes and
that's not good and so I'm trying to
convey that to people it's
you have there's actually something that
you need to do you need to take care of
yourself you need to take care of your
family you need to take care of your
community and if you don't do that
then they'll be hell to pay and it's on
you right each of us and it's it's hard
for people to grasp that because well
they don't want to first of all me
because they don't want the
responsibility but then they don't get
any meaning then they suffer then they
get better that's not good so it's like
which of these are you gonna pick but
it's also salutary to people because
it's useful for everyone to know that if
you don't live up to your potential that
you leave a hole in the fabric of being
and it's filled by something
approximating hell and unless that's
what you want then you shouldn't be
doing that and so and it's perfectly
possible to have a serious discussion
with 3,000 people about this and they're
right on board with it all the way and
so that's really something amazing to
behold and one of the things I've
realized is though these new
technologies the technologies you're
using that enable these long-form
discussions turns out that people are
smarter than we thought right right
right
TV narrowed it right so 30 seconds say
your complicated thing in 30 seconds
like like can't and so we were viewing
the the population through this narrow
window and everyone looked kind of
stupid it's like now the windows fully
open it's like oh look at that you
people like 40 hour Netflix specials
that are incredibly complex right and
you like three hours Joe Rogan
discussions that are complicated you'll
follow the whole thing it's like oh good
we're smarter than we thought thank God
for that
is we better be so yeah so that's that's
where I mean oh yeah yeah yeah okay
question number two this is called
you've got the twelve rules for life
make sure you guys again go pick it up
get it right now what's the link as well
oh now fourth ring dot-com and I put up
a code which is greatness greatness 20%
off you know suite two for one so you
can give the suite to your friends to
self yourself authoring calm yeah not
some slash grandmas just the code is
gracious the code is great it's yeah and
say that and I would say to everyone if
gonna try this exercise which I would
recommend do it over a few days and
don't do it perfectly just do it get it
done do a bad first draft which is an
important principle in life a bad first
draft is a great thing to have that's
good yeah you're also on Instagram
Twitter or Facebook yeah yeah so we'll
make all that stuff up okay yep and your
website what's your main website Jordan
B Peterson dot-com perfect okay so make
sure you guys get the book subscribe to
everything get the self authoring the
the future offering for you University
students out there the future authoring
program decreases your probability of
dropout if you're in a college program
university program by somewhere between
25 and 50 percent especially if you're
kind of aimless it works better if you
if you already got a plan and you're
implementing it you've got a good
direction then you know it's not as
helpful because you're already halfway
there but if you're kind of lost and you
do this it'll help you not only
establish your goals but stick to them
it really helps we've done three very
detailed published peer-reviewed studies
showing that this really works yeah and
it doesn't hurt you either that's the
other thing that's great so it's great
you've got the 12 wolf left I've got
something called the three truths it's a
question I ask everyone at the end and
so we're trying to boil this down for
three truths for you you know imagine
this is your last day you get to choose
the day for you when you die yeah as
many years away as we want it to be and
you've achieved your purpose everything
you set out you aim for you hit the
target
hmm and then you know you pass away it's
the last day everyone's there it's a
celebration yeah but for whatever reason
there's no more videos of you up online
there's no more lectures no more podcast
no more books for whatever reason you
have to take them with you mm-hmm
so no one has access to your information
mm-hmm but you get to a piece of paper
and you get to write down three things
you know to be true about your life that
you would pass on I like to call it the
three don't say things that make you
weak I'm one who lifts your eyes above
the horizon a name at the highest star
that you can contemplate
what's the third one put your family in
order hmm yeah before I ask the final
question I want to acknowledge you for a
moment Jordan for your incredible wisdom
and vulnerability with me we just met
but I feel very connected to you and
your mission and your purpose and I just
appreciate everything you've been
through as a father and as a husband for
your for your daughter for your son for
your wife to continue to move on in your
own dreams in pursuit of bettering
humanity while going through all that
you've gone through so I really
acknowledge everything you've been doing
and what you stand for and your ability
to use your words carefully to make sure
to try to make the best impact on people
who are listening so I'll make Knology
for all that I hope we get to have you
come back sometime when you're in LA
because I think we can go for another
album too and the final question is
what's your definition of greatness
well greatness is what reveals itself
when you when you attempt to formulate
when you attempt to carefully articulate
and live out what you believe to be true
it just happens because there isn't
anything more powerful than truth right
that's the antidote to suffering truth
right so it's a strange thing because
you think well yeah it produces a lot of
suffering too it's like yeah in the
short term yeah so yeah thank you sir
you bet thanks for the invitation and
the opportunity very nice to meet you
yeah thank you all right
you